在过去60年左右的时间里
Over the last 60 years or so,
洲际弹道导弹(ICBM)已成为
intercontinental Ballistic missiles or ICBM's have become the ultimate deterrent in the defence arsenals
美英俄中法和其他国家国防军火库中的终极威慑力量
of the US, UK, Russia, China, France and other countries.
这就产生了相互保证毁灭理论(MAD理论/共同毁灭原则)
This produced the doctrine of M.A.D. or Mutually Assured Destruction
即如果发生核冲突，没有人能活到最后
where if there was a nuclear conflict, no one would come out a winner.
但近年来，随着反弹道导弹系统(ABM系统)变得更加完善
But as anti-ballistic missile systems or ABM's have become better in recent years,
有人认为，在某一时刻，拥有完善的ABM系统的国家在进行首次打击后
there is the belief that at some point a first strike by a country with a fully developed ABM system
若能完美防御随后的报复性反击 则有可能在核冲突中取胜
could lead to a winnable nuclear conflict if the retaliatory strike could be neutralised.
然而，在过去的十年里，人们一直在研发一种新的高超音速武器
However, in the last decade or so a new class of hypersonic weapons has been in development
它不仅能够在创纪录的时间内将弹头送达目标
that promises to be able to not only deliver a warhead to a target in record time
并且几乎不可能被拦截击落
but to do it in such a way as to make it almost impossible to shoot them down,
那么 高超音速导弹与十年前的ICMB的老技术相比 到底有什么优势呢？
so how do Hypersonic missiles compare to the decade's old tech of ICMB's and are they really any better ?
本视频由Brilliant赞助
This video is sponsored by Brilliant.
那么什么是高超音速导弹？为什么它会在新的军备竞赛中引起如此多的关注呢？
So what are hypersonic missiles and why are they causing so much concern in a new arms race.
首先 我们先看一下ICBM的全称“洲际弹道导弹” 顾名思义
Well, first we have to look at ICBM's and the clue is in the name, Intercontinental “Ballistic” Missile,
指在重力作用下的弹道物体
a ballistic object is one which is following a path under the force of gravity.
从枪里射出的子弹或从飞机上投下的炸弹等也都属于弹道武器
A bullet fired from a gun or a bomb dropped from a plane are also examples of ballistic weapons,
一旦发射或释放 它们就会遵循可预测的轨迹
once they have been fired or released they follow a predictable trajectory.
ICBM也不例外 如果从地球表面上的一个点发射
An ICBM is no different, if one is launched from one point on the earth's surface
然后对准另一个可能在数千公里外的点 那它每次都会遵循相同的轨迹
and aimed at another point maybe thousands of kilometres away will follow the same path each time.
首先它被发射进入太空 即发射阶段
It will launch up into space, the launch phase,
然后在太空中飞行 积累速度
fly through space where builds up its speed
并在动力作用下进行航向修正 即中段飞行阶段
and does any course correction whilst still under power, the mid course phase,
然后有效载荷脱离 弹头和诱饵诱饵弹落到指定的目标
then the payload will detach and the warheads and decoys will then fall to their assigned targets,
即下降阶段
the descent phase.
因为ICBM飞得很高 所以可以很容易被雷达和天基跟踪观察到
Because the ICBM's fly high they can be easily observed with radar and space-based tracking.
在中段飞行阶段 它们最容易受到攻击
It's in the midcourse phase where they are most vulnerable
它们的飞行轨迹可以被计算出来 以便ABM系统拦截
and their trajectory can be worked out for to ABM's to intercept them.
虽然这存在理论上的可行性 但实际操作仍然极其困难
Whilst this is do-able it is still extremely difficult
就好像用子弹打子弹一样
and is described as like shooting a bullet with a bullet.
美国在反导系统开发方面已经花了几十年的时间
The US has spent decades in developing ABM systems
只有在最近几年才有了一个可行的解决方案
and its only the last few years that they could say they had a workable solution
但它也只能同时对付少量的来袭导弹
but it can only deal with a small number of incoming missiles at once
而且在战略上只能拦截2到3枚从太平洋那边飞来的来自朝鲜的导弹
and is strategically placed to intercept may 2 or 3 coming in over the Pacific from North Korea.
现在想象一下 你可以发射一枚飞行速度和ICBM一样快的导弹
Now imagine that you could launch a missile that would travel as fast as ICBM
但不是让它从太空中落到目标身上
but instead of having it just fall from space on to its target,
而是像巡航导弹一样飞行并采取回避行动
it could fly like a cruise missile and take evasive action.
这对于目前的ABM系统来说几乎是不可能阻挡的
This now becomes virtually unstoppable with current ABM systems,
而这也正是中俄两国正在做的事情
and this is exactly what the Russians and Chinese are doing
因为他们认为 如果美国能够让其ABM系统对付更多来袭的导弹
because they believe that if the US can make its ABM systems tackle a much greater number of missiles
那么战争的天平就会向美国倾斜
the balance of power would shift to the US
让美国知道自己可以防御报复性的反击 从而决定发动首轮打击
and allow it to make a first strike knowing it could destroy any missiles sent in retaliation.
高超音速武器分为两类：高超音速滑翔导弹和高超音速巡航导弹
There are two categories of Hypersonic weapons, hypersonic glide vehicles and hypersonic cruise missiles.
高超音速滑翔飞行器的工作原理有点像ICBM
Hypersonic glide vehicles work a bit like an ICBM
它们是用火箭发射到太空中
in that they are launched on a rocket into space
但随后下降到大气层的顶部
but then they descend to the top of the atmosphere
利用飞行器的机体产生的冲击波
and use the shockwave created the body of the craft
利用一种叫做“压缩升力”的现象在大气层顶部打水漂
in a phenomenon called compression lift to skim across it,
然后当它接近目标时下降 像一个可操纵的高超音速滑翔机一样
then as it nears its target it drops down and acts like a steerable hypersonic glider
这使得反导防御系统更难瞄准
which makes it much more difficult to target by anti-missile defence systems.
高超音速巡航导弹也可以用火箭或飞机发射
Hypersonic cruise missiles can also be launched on a rocket or from a plane
但它们并不进入太空 而是像普通巡航导弹那样在大气层内飞行
but instead of going into space, they fly through the atmosphere like a normal cruise missile.
不同之处在于它们的速度
The difference is in their speed,
它们没有像战斧巡航导弹那样使用传统的喷气式发动机
instead of using a conventional jet engine like in the Tomahawk cruise missile,
而是使用超音速燃烧冲压发动机(SCRAMjet)以4马赫以上的速度飞行
they use a SCRAMjet engine which only works above MACH 4
所以最初必须用火箭提升到这个速度 然后让SCRAMjet接管
so they have to initially boosted to that speed by a rocket, then the SCRAMjet takes over.
这就是高超音速导弹的优势所在
This is where hypersonic missiles have the upper hand
因为它们可以使用飞行高度更低的低空弹道
because they can use what is known as depressed trajectory to fly much lower
但对于滑翔导弹 它仍可以进行最高25马赫的高超音速飞行
but still at hypersonic speeds of upto MACH 25 for the gliders,
这样它们可以在被发现之前就能接近目标
so they can get closer to the target before being detected.
这不仅给对手留下了极少的时间来确定其飞行路线
This not only leaves very little time for the opponent to figure out their course,
它们还可以在现有的ABM系统下飞行
they can also fly under existing ABM systems
因为ABM系统设计是寻找并拦截从太空中高空飞来的ICBM并预测其轨迹
which are designed to look for and intercept ICBM's coming in high from space and on a predictable trajectory.
它们的高超音速性质使它们在低空几乎不可能被击落
Their hypersonic speed makes them almost impossible to shoot down at low altitude
并且有机动能力 使其飞行轨迹无法预测
and they can manoeuvre so their course can't be predicted.
高超音速巡航导弹也被吹捧为威力巨大的反舰导弹
Hypersonic cruise missiles have also be touted as extremely potent anti-ship missiles
因为即使没有弹头 以5马赫或更快的速度击中航母也会造成大破
because even without a warhead, hitting an aircraft carrier at MACH 5 or above would cause a lot of damage,
可能不会击沉 但很可能使其失去战斗能力
it may not sink the ship but it would more than likely put it out of action.
但高超音速导弹有一个问题 它影响了所有正在发展高超音速导弹的国家
But there is a problem with hypersonic missiles which is affecting all the countries who are developing them
而这个问题是由高超音速导弹的优势所造成的——它的速度
and its caused by the very thing that gives them their advantage, namely their speed.
在大气层中以高超音速飞行会产生大量的热量 且会随着速度的增加而增加
Flying at hypersonic speeds in the atmosphere creates a tremendous amount of heat which increases with speed.
黑鸟SR-71侦察机在7万英尺高空以3.2马赫的速度飞行
The SR-71 Blackbird spy plane flew at MACH 3.2 at 70,000 ft
空气的密度只有海平面上的5%
where the air is only about 5% the density of that at sea level
导致机翼的前缘温度高达560摄氏度
and that caused the leading edges of its wings to reach up to 560 degrees Celsius,
足以熔化一些铝合金
that's hot enough to melt some aluminium alloys.
ICBM的弹头在最后的下降阶段也是以高超音速飞行
The ball head's of ICBM's also travel at hypersonic speeds during their final descent stage
但只有一两分钟
but only for a minute or two,
并且使用了防热盾来保护它们 类似再入的航天器
and use an ablative heat shield to protect them much like returning spacecraft,
而对于高超音速武器
hypersonic weapons on the other hand,
它们则要全程以5马赫以上的速度飞行上千公里
travel the almost there entire journey which could be thousands of kilometres at MACH 5 and above.
在海平面 空气最密集的地方 高超音速导弹的最大速度约为7马赫
At sea level where the air is at its densest, the maximum speed of a hypersonic missile is about MACH 7.
在这种速度下产生的热量会使导弹的材料超过2000摄氏度
The heat created at these speeds can cause the materials of the missiles are made out of
to exceed 2000 degrees Celsius
因此必须用特种复合材料制成
so they have to be made of exotic composites.
在这种温度下 空气开始与材料发生化学反应 导致材料分解
At these temperatures the air starts to chemically react with the materials, causing them to break down.
它的温度也会高到使飞行器周围形成等离子体
It's also hot enough to cause plasma to form around the vehicle
从而影响到GPS制导系统和从外部向其发送的航向修正指令
which can affect the GPS guidance systems and course correction commands sent to it from outside.
而这会影响到导弹的精度
This affects the accuracy of the missile.
在高超音速状态下 风 温度等环境因素的变化会被放大
At hypersonic speeds variations in the wind, temperature and other environmental factors are magnified
这就使得相比于普通亚音速巡航弹 命中像舰艇这样的目标要难得多
making it much more difficult to target sth like a ship accurately compared to normal subsonic cruise missile.
高超音速武器还使被攻击的国家领导者处于非常困难的境地
Hypersonic weapons also place the leaders of the country being targeted in a very difficult position
因为当导弹以每秒几公里的速度飞过地平线时
because there is virtually no difference between a nuclear-armed missile and a conventionally armed missile
它装不装核弹头已经不重要了
when it comes barrelling over the horizon at several kilometres per second
而决策者又没有多少时间作出反应 可能只是下令进行全面报复
and with so little time to react they might just order an all-out retaliation
而不是等着看一会爆炸有多大
rather than wait to see how big the bang is
这就是高超音速武器目前地位不确定的原因
and this is why they are seen as so destabilising.
目前 除了同样奇葩的定向能武器之外 没有什么能阻止它们
At the moment there is nothing much that can stop them except the equally exotic directed-energy weapons
这比高超音速武器本身走得还要远
which even further down the pipeline than the Hypersonic weapons themselves.
但随着空间探测技术的升级
But with upgraded space based detection
人们将有可能从发射时就能追踪到高超音速导弹的热量
it will be possible to track the hot missile bodies almost from their launch
这将给人们与ICBM相同的预警时间
which will give about the same amount of warning time as that of an ICBM.
这在一段时间内不太可能影响到国家之间力量的平衡
So it's unlikely to affect the balance of power for a while because
因为现在防御几十到几百枚ICBM的全面攻击还做不到
there is still no practical way to defend against a full-scale attack from dozens to hundreds of ICBM's,
所以即使俄罗斯或中国拥有几百枚高超音速导弹
so even if Russia or China were to have hundreds of hypersonic missiles,
美国至少还有1500枚弹头可以进行报复
the US still has at least 1500 warheads that it could retaliate with.
现在 美国在高超音速武器方面也稍微追赶上来了
Now the US has been seen as in a bit of a catch up situation on hypersonic weapons
即使美国跟着研究了几十年 中俄两国在这方面也一直走在前沿
with both China and Russia taking the lead even though the US has been working with them for decades.
美国的想法是 死磕ABM系统就够了
The thinking in the US being that an ABM shield was a better approach,
而高超音速技术的出现则让我们明白
something which now we can see can be side stepped with hypersonic technology
科学技术不会停滞不前
which just illustrates the point that things don't stand still,
今天的好主意放到明天可能就馊了
what's a good idea today isn't necessarily going to be a good idea tomorrow
你必须不断学习新的技能和技术
and you have to keep learning new skills and techniques,
于是就到了猝不及防时间
which brings me on to our sponsor for this video Brilliant.
Brilliant is a problem-solving website that can help you develop your learning skills
by breaking complex problems down to small easily understandable parts
then putting back together to show the overall solution build-up to reach the conclusion.
There are loads of great totally interactive courses and as we saw in this video,
missiles are all about maths and kinematics,
the language of everything that moves so why not start with projectile motion
and how arrows follow a ballistic path along with much more.
This hands-on active learning approach is great for curious people like you
who want to understand the world.
If you want to support Curious Droid
and get unlimited access to all of Brilliant's in-depth math and science courses,
head over to brilliant.org/curiousdroid/ to get 20% off their annual Premium subscription.